<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-13T08:38:48+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/feed.xml</id><title type="html">juan’s virtual book</title><entry><title type="html">what I’m doing now #20</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-20" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I’m doing now #20" /><published>2026-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-20"><![CDATA[<!--more-->

<h3 id="looking-to-buy-a-home">looking to buy a home</h3>

<p>It’s a great time to get into the Vancouver housing market.
Z found us an agent and now we’re working with a mortgage broker.
Today we toured four properties.
I have to remind myself to be patient, wait for the right opportunity.
It’s hard not to get excited.</p>

<h3 id="enjoying-keith-mckellans-illustrations">enjoying Keith McKellan’s illustrations</h3>

<p>A few years ago Z and I went on a dinner date at <a href="https://thenaam.com/">The Naam</a>, “Vancouver’s Oldest Vegetarian Restaurant.”
Later, Z gifted me a postcard with this illustration of the restaurant:</p>

<p><img src="./assets/images/theNaam.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>I don’t know where that postcard is but I was reminded of it a few days ago when I saw dozens of similar illustrations covering the side of an old van parked at the edge of Commercial Drive.
I stopped and spoke with the artist for a while.
He has made, over the years, fifty of these intricate illustrations depicting quirky cafes and theatres of Vancouver.
They are all on display <a href="https://laughinghand.com/prints_new/printpage.htm">on his site</a>.
They are all also in the coffee table book I bought from him.
I saw him again on The Drive a few days later and bought a large print.
I still have to get a frame for it and decide where to hang it up.
We have a gallery wall but the piece deserves its own section elsewhere in the apartment.</p>

<h3 id="playing-soccer-watching-soccer">playing soccer, watching soccer</h3>

<p>In December of last year our sevens team finally won first place.
It’s a local recreational league that lasts twelve weeks at a time, but for several seasons in a row we’d fallen short, often in the final.
But last season, we finally won.
Obviously it was not a big deal, but, also, it was.
Taking on a challenge and succeeding is gratifying even if there are no real stakes.</p>

<p>Arsenal, on the other hand, is playing for high stakes.
The team is fantastic, but they’ve won nothing yet.
Hopefully come summertime they’ll have trophies to flaunt.
Unfortunately not even that will deter the haters.
I would call soccerfan culture zerosum but it’s probably in the negatives.</p>

<h3 id="thinking-about-narcissism">thinking about narcissism</h3>

<p>For Secret Santa a friend of mine gave me a Bob’s Burgers cookbook.
It was a thoughtful gift (he knows I love Bob’s Burgers) but I don’t use cookbooks so I took it to a bookshop to exchange for another book.
I used the opportunity to pick up <em>The Culture of Narcissism</em> by Christopher Lasch.
Owning thoughtprovoking nonfiction books is great because it affords reading in bouts and digesting over time.</p>

<p>I read the first two chapters in January and have been thinking about them.
I’ve also been watching <em>The Sopranos</em> for the third time and noticing the intense narcissism of Anthony Soprano’s character.
I’m dismayed to realize that his apparent morality originates from feelings of worthlessness and selfloathing.
He is a complex character.
At times he appears moral, even good.
But I’m beginning to see how thoroughly polluted he is.
He’s noxious, not just ultimately, but fundamentally.
Not because he was born that way, but because the poison instilled in him in his upbringing he buries more deeply because he’s too afraid to unearth it.</p>

<h3 id="watching-movies">watching movies</h3>

<p><em>Marty Supreme</em> –
Fun, but not very compelling.</p>

<p><em>Hamnet</em> –
Beautiful, but flawed.</p>

<p><em>Arco</em> –
Special, and heartfelt.
Fun, as well.</p>

<p><em>Heat</em> –
Overrated because it looks and sounds good.</p>

<p><em>The Boy and the Heron</em> –
Viscerally provocative.
Confusing.</p>

<p><em>Send Help</em> –
Entertaining, funny, but unambitious.</p>

<p><em>Train Dreams</em> –
Gorgeous.
Restrained.
Moving.</p>

<p>Reviewed in more words on <a href="https://letterboxd.com/okjuanito/reviews/">my Letterboxd</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shopping for a home, supporting local art, playing & watching soccer, contemplating narcissism, watching movies & TV.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what is restraint?</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/on-restraint" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what is restraint?" /><published>2026-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/on-restraint"><![CDATA[<!--more-->

<p>Restraint is <a id="2024-02-04-use-restraint" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/restraint">omitting an ingredient</a> because it would undermine more important ones.</p>

<p>Restraint is knowing the point when <a id="2025-06-09-use-restraint-2" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/restraint-2">riches become burdens</a> because things cost more than their price.</p>

<p>Restraint is recognizing that <a id="2025-08-28-restraint" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/restraint-3">technology and the convenience it provides</a> is a sort of alienation.</p>

<p>Restraint is <a id="2026-01-30-restraint" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/restraint-4">avoiding selfindulgence</a> to allow that others may trust in your jugdment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to revise a sentence #7</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to revise a sentence #7" /><published>2026-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/revise-a-sentence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint-7"><![CDATA[<p>Here is Paul Harding in <em>Tinkers</em> relating a boy’s attempt to run away from home.
<!--more--></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The sunny weekend morning, the lackadaisical mule, and the extra heaviness of the slow rate imparted by the bulk of the wagon conspired to dilute [the boy]’s half notions of speed and flight and pursuit and evasion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Easy to notice is <a id="2026-01-30-restraint" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/restraint-4">Harding’s excess</a> in phrases like <em>the extra heaviness of the slow rate imparted by the bulk of the wagon</em> and <em>speed and flight and pursuit and evasion</em>.
Do we really need all these words?
But the sentence has a more fundamental issue.
Why personify the circumstances into “conspiring” agents?
It’s a creative formulation, but does it contribute anything to what is being expressed?</p>

<p>The point of inventive wording, I think, is to illuminate the subject by casting particular light on it.
Phrasing should be effective, not affected.
Why did Harding choose this phrasing?
A humbler one would eschew wordy choices like <em>conspire</em> and <em>impart</em> to allow apt words like <em>dilute</em>, <em>deflate</em>, or <em>dissipate</em> to play the central role in the idea being conveyed.
Something like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The boy’s notions of flight and pursuit dissipated as he sat on this bulky wagon towed by this lackadaisical mule on this sunny weekend morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Already, the sentence is more faithful to its meaning.
We’ve halved <em>speed and flight and pursuit and evasion</em> into <em>flight and pursuit</em> and reconfigured the sentence to make its verb, <em>dissipated</em>, relevant to the sentence’s principal message: reality is deflating the boy’s fantasy of running away.
We no longer state that the boy’s fantasy is slipping away because of his circumstances, but we imply it.</p>

<p>The second half of our new sentence is a bit monotonous.
Further iteration can help:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The boy’s notions of flight and pursuit dissipated as the wagon trundled along in the sunny weekend morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’ve removed explicit mention of the <em>lackadaisical mule</em> and the <em>bulky</em> nature of the wagon in favor of a useful verb: <em>trundled</em>.
However, we have somewhat weakened the implication that the slowness of the escape vehicle and the pleasant weather are to blame for the boy’s change in mood.
We can also try another structure:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As the wagon trundled along through the sunny weekend morning, the boy’s notions of flight and pursuit dissipated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Not only does this sentence strengthen the implication of the causual relationship between the environment and the boy’s psychology, it also heightens the sense of passing time in which the boy’s fantasies gradually lose their believability.</p>

<p>But this effect ends abruptly because the sentence ends immediately after the word <em>dissipated</em>.
We can draw out the sense further by making space at the end of the sentence into which the dissipation can extend in the way its meaning suggests:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As the wagon trundled along, the boy’s notions of flight and pursuit dissipated into the sunny weekend morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At this point, we have space for the <em>lackadaisical mule</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As the mule shuffled along and the wagon trundled behind it, the boy’s notions of flight and pursuit dissipated into the sunny weekend morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Lackadaisical</em> is a fun word indeed, but <em>As the wagon trundled along behind the lackadaisical mule</em> dissatisfies me.
I prefer <em>the mule shuffled</em>, I think it creates a more vivid image in the mind.
There’s good reason for the rule of thumb Verbs over Adjectives.
They help to <a id="2021-01-10-make.instead.of.describing" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/make-instead-of-describing">make instead of describing</a>.
Fancy words and fancy phrasings tend to contribute less than they provide.
Their sacrifice allows the spotlight to fall on the content instead of falling on the writer, and ultimately, in a quieter way, this reflects well on the writer.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here is Paul Harding in Tinkers relating a boy’s attempt to run away from home.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to use restraint #4</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to use restraint #4" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/restraint-4"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinkers_(novel)"><em>Tinkers</em></a> by Paul Harding because I enjoyed listening to <a href="https://youtu.be/roLRPQPQU58?si=AUVnKRXHxkZ7BWQN">him speak</a> about his writing process, but his writing style has somewhat disappointed me.
<!--more--></p>

<p>One of the many vignettes in his book begins with this modest sentence:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Ninety-six hours before he died, George said he wanted a shave.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a good sentence and, in a sense, a perfect sentence.
It has no flaws.
It does its job and nothing else.
It states two facts in plain terms and allows all meaning to arise from their juxtaposition, the irony of personal grooming at the edge of personal oblivion.</p>

<p>We learn that, for all his adult life, George kept a daily habit of shaving to stave off his beard of <em>mangy patches</em>.
(Supposedly, only a day’s stubble <em>lent him the look of an invalid or a large child incapable of taking care of his own needs.</em>)
But in his dotage and ill health, George’s shaving routine has faltered.
So he asks his family if they might shave him, and one of his adult grandchildren, Sam, volunteers.</p>

<p>Harding gives details like the <em>bowl of scalding water</em> and the <em>cheap disposable plastic razor</em> that are relevant and meaningful because they foreshadow Sam’s carelessness and invoke us readers to sympathize with George.
But Harding also includes details that seem irrelevant and consequently dilute and distract from the meaningful ones.
He mentions that the razor was found by the grandmother <em>in a basket beneath the bathroom sink that was filled with various disused, soap-crusted toiletry.</em>
I think <em>soap-crusted</em> is the most excessive detail here, but I think the entire phrase could have been removed.
Harding is giving us too much.
Only to a certain extent do vivid descriptions make things more vivid to the reader.
At some point, they stop deepening the feeling of immersion in a fictional world and start drawing attention instead to the author and his stylishness as a writer.</p>

<p>We readers have already a reservoir of vivid images we draw from when reading fiction.
It is enough to say that the grandmother found a razor in her own house.
That alone can conjure an image of a bathroom cupboard full of nonessential toiletry.
And even if it does not, it conveys the relevant facts.
Firstly, that George’s usual shaving equipment will not be used.
And secondly, that for some bothersome reason George’s wife does not know where that equipment is or has neglected to find it.
These subtle, meaningful implications are more salient to readers when the author does not distract them with other, irrelevant information.</p>

<p>Fiction is a collaboration between author and audience.
Readers experience the same work differently, sometimes drastically so.
The same reader returning a work encounters it with new eyes.
To write with restraint is to withhold one’s creative surplus to make space for the reader’s reflections and ruminations.
Every word, every detail the author provides is an invitation to the reader to consider something and therefore also a dismissal of their considerations.
Detail and specificity become eventual enemies of depth and expanse.</p>

<p>A few sentences later in <em>Tinkers</em> comes another example of overwriting:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The can [of shaving cream] was old, excavated along with the razor from the guts of the cabinet under the bathroom sink.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The word <em>excavated</em> is a needlessly stylish alternative to the typical and sufficient “dug up.”
Even a simple “taken” would’ve served.
More indulgent than <em>excavated</em> is <em>guts</em>, which is an empty metaphor for “inside.”
It suggests a deeper meaning that is not there.
In indulgent moments like these, the quality of the novel degrades from vivid to lurid.
(In context of the whole book, this particular choice of <em>guts</em> suffers further from the fact that Harding had already used it metaphorically twice when referring to the internals of clocks and goes on to use it in such a way another three times.
It’s an evocative description but Harding washes it out with overuse.)</p>

<p>It’s not a sin to flex your muscles as a writer if you do so by building something compelling.
But I think Harding succumbs to the temptation of making pointless flourishes and embellisments all too often, especially for a novel that was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010_Pulitzer_Prize">awarded the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="literature" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been reading Tinkers by Paul Harding because I enjoyed listening to him speak about his writing process, but his writing style has somewhat disappointed me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what is alienation?</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/alienation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what is alienation?" /><published>2026-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/alienation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/alienation"><![CDATA[<p>A sort of alienation easy to understand is the kind that keeps people apart.
<!--more-->
A subtler sort is the kind that estranges a person from their own potential by diminishing their powers as an individual.
Here is Christopher Lasch in his book <em>The Culture of Narcissism</em> writing on the topic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The contemporary American may have failed, like his predecessors, to establish any sort of common life, but the integrating tendencies of modern industrial society have at the same time undermined his “isolation.” Having surrendered most of his technical skills to the corporation, he can no longer provide for his material needs. As the family loses not only its productive functions but many of its reproductive functions as well, men and women no longer manage even to raise their children without the help of certified experts. The atrophy of older traditions of self-help has eroded everyday competence, in one area after another, and has made the individual dependent on the state, the corporation, and other bureaucracies.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="quotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A sort of alienation easy to understand is the kind that keeps people apart.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I’m doing now #19</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-19" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I’m doing now #19" /><published>2026-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-19"><![CDATA[<!--more-->

<h3 id="getting-back-to-work">getting back to work</h3>

<p>In late September <a id="2025-09-23-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-16">I thought</a> things at work would slow down for me, but then I got immediately pulled into an exciting new project.
I worked on it up until the Friday before my vacation started in mid December.
For the four weeks I was in Mexico – <a id="2025-12-16-yucatan" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/yucatan">three in the Yucatan Peninsula</a> and <a id="2026-01-09-mexico-city" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/cdmx">one in Mexico City</a> – I didn’t do any work.
In the last few days of my vacation a feeling of foreboding crept up in me.
A creeping fear of failure.</p>

<p>I’d halted work on my project and now I had to get back into it without the momentum I’d built up.
This week I’ve been getting back into gear.
The work is interesting and challenging.
My role in the project is significant, I have an opportunity to make a big impact.
I’m excited.</p>

<h3 id="being-wary-of-my-time">being wary of my time</h3>

<p>It’s easy to say yes to things.
Yes I’ll go to the party.
Yes let’s get lunch.
Yes let’s invite people over.
Yes let’s go on that trip.
Then the day comes and you wonder, Did I even <em>want</em> to do this or was I just taking the easy option?</p>

<p>Balance is hard to find.
How many friends are enough?
Can one have too many?
What about hobbies?</p>

<p>My wife Z gets anxious after socializing.
<em>Did I do something weird?</em>
I thought it was a quirk I didn’t relate to but then I noticed I get anxious <em>before</em> socializing.
As the scheduled time approaches, I start squirming mentally.
I regret committing to it.
I feel trapped.
But is that really because it was a mistake or is it because I feel anxious?</p>

<p>I suppose the answer is simple, ultimately.
Your body tells you.
It tells you if you should’ve gotten more exercise, more sleep, more food, more water, it even tells you if you accomplished enough in the day.
The difficult part is listening.
You have to learn how to tune into the frequency of those silent messages and how to decipher them.
Are you really annoyed or are you just overcaffeinated?
Are you really angry or are you just hungry?</p>

<p>Most of most days I pipe podcasts and sports commentary into my brain.
For years now I’ve listened to the same old comedy podcast to fall asleep.
These days I play sitcom compilations on my phone.
I didn’t think much of it but recently I’ve noticed that it’s external chatter I introduce to quiet my internal chatter.
Without it, I find my mind turning over and over on the same old things.
To my surprise I find myself relating to the idea of thoughts that “keep you up at night.”
For how long has it been like this?
It’s possible I’m just drinking too much coffee and not getting enough exercise.
I haven’t figured it out yet.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">trip to Mexico City</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/cdmx" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="trip to Mexico City" /><published>2026-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/mexico-city</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/cdmx"><![CDATA[<p>After <a id="2025-12-16-yucatan" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/yucatan">vacationing in the Yucatan Peninsula</a>, my younger sister and I went to Mexico City to visit family.
<!--more--></p>

<h4 id="sunday-01042026--merida--mexico-city">Sunday 01/04/2026 – Merida → Mexico City</h4>

<ul>
  <li>land &amp; disembark @ 10:30am; take taxi to our aunt &amp; uncle’s house in el Pedregal</li>
  <li>drink coffee &amp; chat w/ my uncle G</li>
  <li>watch second half of Chelsea vs Man City until my grandpa &amp; my aunt T arrived</li>
  <li>sit &amp; chat w/ my grandpa; drink a beer &amp; a tequila w/ him while my cousins E &amp; E &amp; their dad J arrived</li>
  <li>eat an assortment of meats that my uncle G grilled: chistorra, Argentine chorizo, arrachera, &amp; rib-eye</li>
  <li>drink coffee, eat cookies, &amp; chat</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="monday-01052026--mexico-city-palmas">Monday 01/05/2026 – Mexico City (Palmas)</h4>

<ul>
  <li>sit in patio and write <a id="2026-01-05-my-life" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/life"><em>what I am doing with my life</em></a> &amp; other bits</li>
  <li>eat lunch @ kitchen table w/ my sister, my aunt C, &amp; my cousin G</li>
  <li>hang out &amp; chat in living room, drinking coffee &amp; eating cookies</li>
  <li>watch <em>The Holdovers</em> w/ my sister &amp; cousin G</li>
  <li>supper @ Taqueria Los Atarantados</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="tuesday-01062026--mexico-city-el-pedregal--santa-fe">Tuesday 01/06/2026 – Mexico City (El Pedregal &amp; Santa Fe)</h4>

<ul>
  <li>play tennis w/ my sister &amp; cousin G</li>
  <li>lunch @ Los Canarios in Perisur w/ my sister, my aunt C, &amp; my cousin C</li>
  <li>dillydally @ Centro Santa Fe &amp; then Parque La Mexicana</li>
  <li>supper &amp; rosca de reyes @ my aunt T’s house with aunts T, C, &amp; S as well as several cousins &amp; their partners</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="wednesday-01072026--mexico-city-roma-norte">Wednesday 01/07/2026 – Mexico City (Roma Norte)</h4>

<ul>
  <li>relax &amp; drink coffee</li>
  <li>spend the afternoon w/ my grandpa at his senior’s home w/ my sister &amp; aunt C</li>
  <li>look at photo albums; eat lunch; play a board game; accompany my grandpa up to the gym</li>
  <li>meet w/ my childhood friend J</li>
  <li>beer @ La Roma Brewing then tacohopping @ Taquerias La Taque then @ Taqueria Los Atarantados</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="thursday-01082026--mexico-city-la-condesa--toluca">Thursday 01/08/2026 – Mexico City (La Condesa) &amp; Toluca</h4>

<ul>
  <li>go to Mexican Federation of Football w/ my uncle G, my cousin G, and my sister</li>
  <li>tour the office; get a tutorial from folks who run the VAR; watch bits of a youth match at one of the fields</li>
  <li>have pizza for lunch while watching Arsenal vs Liverpool on patio</li>
  <li>spend time w/ my grandpa; play a board game with him, my sister, &amp; my aunt C</li>
  <li>check in for flight; struggle through app errors</li>
  <li>supper @ El Tizoncito in La Condesa w/ a group of cousins</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="friday-01092026--mexico-city">Friday 01/09/2026 – Mexico City</h4>

<ul>
  <li>wake @ 9am, say goodbye to my uncle, drink coffee, and journal</li>
  <li>breakfast @ kitchen table w/ my aunt C &amp; cousin G</li>
  <li>more coffee &amp; journaling; pack, shower, and leave for airport</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="travel" /><category term="family" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After vacationing in the Yucatan Peninsula, my younger sister and I went to Mexico City to visit family.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I am doing with my life</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I am doing with my life" /><published>2026-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/my-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/life"><![CDATA[<!--more-->

<h3 id="1996---2007">1996 - 2007</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Living in Mexico City.
Playing sports.
Playing soccer, obsessively.
Wondering if I’ll be better than Pelé.</p>

<h3 id="2007---2010">2007 - 2010</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Living in Westchester County, New York.
Still playing soccer.
Getting obsessed with First Person Shooters, especially Call of Duty.
Trying to fit in.
Waiting for my growth spurt.</p>

<h3 id="2010---2014">2010 - 2014</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Living in Victoria, British Columbia.
Still playing soccer.
Still playing Call of Duty.
Suddenly popular in school.
Finally growing.
Working for the first time, minimum wage.
Getting into music.
Learning to play guitar, to sing, to write songs, to make beats, to write raps even.</p>

<h3 id="2014---2019">2014 - 2019</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Still living in Victoria.
Still playing soccer.
Studying at the University of Victoria, a combined major in Music &amp; Computer Science.
Listening to more music, exploring.
Now obsessed with computer programming.
Switched to Computer Science.
Keen to work at a tech company.
First girlfriend.
First car.
Internships.
First trips without my family.
First breakup.
First fulltime job.</p>

<h3 id="2019---2020">2019 - 2020</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Living in Seattle, Washington.
Playing soccer.
Working full time for Microsoft.
Hating it.
Transferring.
Contented.
Coding for personal projects.
Listening to old music.
Reading.
Writing.
Meeting Z.</p>

<h3 id="2020---2025">2020 - <a id="2025-01-18-my-2025" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2025">2025</a></h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Dating Z.
Getting more serious about writing.
Spending time in Victoria.
Losing my brother.
Returning to Seattle.
Making things work with Z.
Transferring again.
Happy.
Making new friends.
Playing soccer.
Traveling.
Splitting time between Vancouver and Seattle.
Getting married.
Getting to know Vancouver.
Making new friends.
Playing soccer.
Watching Arsenal religiously.</p>

<h3 id="2026"><a id="2025-10-28-my-2026" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2026">2026</a></h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Travel to Indonesia.
Learn Indonesian.
Travel to Mexico.
Help Z learn Spanish.
Travel to Toronto?
to PEI?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="2028---2030">2028 - 2030</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Have kids with Z.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="2038">2038</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Take Z and the kids to Bacalar &amp; Calakmul.
Maybe Holbox too.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="2078">2078</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
I looked up life expectancy last summer.
I might live to eightytwo or so.
It’s not the most optimistic projection but it’s certainly not a pessimistic one either.
So, 2078 may be my last year.
We’ll see.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="2085">2085</h3>

<p><em>January 5 2025</em> –
Several weeks ago I watched a video about the Vancouver Sky Train.
It opened in 1985, just in time for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expo_86">Expo 86</a>.
In 2025, the year I watched the video, the Sky Train celebrated its fourtieth anniversary.
When I realized I would likely die before its hundredth anniversary in 2085, it made me very sad.
I had to stop the video so I could cry.
It was almost like grieving my own death, but likely I was just grieving loss in general.
The loss I’ve already endured and the even greater loss that awaits me.
I am yet young and my future is bright but in it also are great, dark clouds and each will approach in their own time to smother and leave me breathless until I also breath my last.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Another live journal, this one the widest in scope.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I did in 2025 #3</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2025-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I did in 2025 #3" /><published>2025-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/my-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2025-4"><![CDATA[<!--more-->

<h3 id="my-2025-in-music">my 2025 in music</h3>

<p>Like I mentioned <a id="2025-01-12-2024-in-review" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2024">last year</a>, I create a playlist every year to collect songs that were special to me.
These playlists are little time capsules that I can unlatch with special attention in the future and be transported into the past.</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px margin-bottom: 15px;" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/5Wqn9De5VzZCaporPbehlM" width="100%" height="352" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="eager"></iframe>

<h3 id="my-2025-in-books">my 2025 in books</h3>

<p>✅ read – ☑️ read (started in a previous year) – ⭕️ unstarted – ⏳ in progress – 🫸 stopped</p>

<h6 id="of-the-books-i-set-out-to-read-at-the-beginning-of-the-year-in-the-order-i-read-them">Of the books I set out to read at the beginning of the year, in the order I read them:</h6>

<ol style="list-style-type: none; margin: 0px">
    <li>✅ <em>The Ginger Man</em></li>
    <li>☑️ <em>The Dominant Animal</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Pachinko</em></li>
    <li>☑️ <em>Blood Meridian</em></li>
    <li>🫸 <em>Mr. Palomar</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Breakfast of Champions</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Wise Blood</em></li>
    <li>🫸 <em>All That Is Solid Melts Into Air</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Circe</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Visit from the Goon Squad</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Malone Dies</em></li>
    <li>⭕️ <em>Song of Solomon</em></li>
    <li>⭕️ <em>Moby Dick</em></li>
    <li>⭕️ <em>Go Down Moses</em></li>
</ol>

<h6 id="books-i-ended-up-reading-along-the-way">Books I ended up reading along the way:</h6>

<ol style="list-style-type: none; margin: 0px">
    <li>🫸 <em>Is A River Alive?</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>Meditations for Mortals</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>A Man Without A Country</em></li>
    <li>🫸 <em>Walden</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>How to Write a Sentence and How to Read One</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>The Medium is the Massage</em></li>
    <li>✅ <em>The Catcher in the Rye</em></li>
    <li>⏳ <em>Tinkers</em></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="my-2025-on-this-site">my 2025 on this site</h3>

<p>This year I wrote many more <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/now</code> updates.
Twelve, in fact!
Some months I wrote multiple, some I wrote none.
I wrote the <a id="2025-12-22-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-18">last one</a> on December 22nd.
From that one you can click back in time through all my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/now</code> updates because this year I implemented a feature that automatically links posts if they are part of a series.
A post is part of a series if its title ends with a number, like <a id="2025-12-22-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-18"><em>what I’m doing now #18</em></a> for example.</p>

<p>Specifically about 2025 I wrote a few pieces, and they were all experimental in form.
Firstly, I wrote <a id="2025-01-18-my-2025" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2025"><em>what I am doing in 2025</em></a>, a “live journal” written incrementally throughout the year.
I also kept a “<a id="2025-05-17-done" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2025-2">done list</a>” of things I did in the whole year.
Finally, at the end of the year, I wrote <a id="2025-12-15-2025-retro" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/2025-3">a retrospective</a> in a new, interactive format I’m calling <em>stacks</em>.</p>

<h3 id="my-2025-in-travel">my 2025 in travel</h3>

<ul>
  <li>In January, I returned from a <a id="2024-12-26-japan-trip" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/japan">trip to Japan</a> I took with my mom, sisters, and our partners.</li>
  <li>In May, I went to Tofino with my mom, sisters, and our partners to celebrate my mom’s birthday for a second year in a row.</li>
  <li>In July, I went with Z to Gibsons BC to celebrate our wedding anniversary.</li>
  <li>In August, I went to <a id="2025-08-07-ireland-trip" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/ireland">Ireland</a> and <a id="2025-08-07-england-trip" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/england">England</a> with Z.</li>
  <li>In December, I <a id="2025-12-16-yucatan" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/yucatan">traveled to the Yucatan Peninsula</a> with Z, my mom, &amp; my younger sister.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="my-2025-in-movies--tv-shows">my 2025 in movies &amp; TV shows</h3>

<p>I watched two movies per month on average.
(A friend of mine who just finished studying film at UBC tries to watch films daily.)
My favorite five were – in no particular order – <em>The Big Lebowski</em> (1998), <em>Dogtooth</em> (2009), <em>One Battle After Another</em> (2025), <em>Lost Highway</em> (1997), and <em>The Florida Project</em> (2017), which I set as one of my four alltime favorite movies on <a href="https://letterboxd.com/okjuanito/">Letterboxd</a>.</p>

<p>I watch a lot of TV in the evenings.
A good deal of it is YouTube content, of which a lot is soccer highlights and commentary about soccer.
Shows I loved include <em>The Studio</em>, <em>The White Lotus</em>, <em>The Pitt</em>, <em>Twin Peaks: The Return</em>, <em>Pluribus</em>, and <em>The Sopranos</em>, my alltime favorite.
I also watched <em>Severance</em> but <a id="2025-03-08-severance" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/severance">didn’t like it much</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What I read, watched, and listened to; where I traveled; some things I did on this site.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beware of all enterprises that require new clothes</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/walden" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beware of all enterprises that require new clothes" /><published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/walden</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/walden"><![CDATA[<p><em>Walden</em> by Henry David Thoreau is a book of ornate prose and provocative ideas.
<!--more-->
In lavish language and oracular voice he indulges in fancies of frugality and abstinence.
It’s a challenging book, stylistically and ideologically.
It feels ambitious and insightful at times, but often also reckless and juvenile.
Its status as a classic of American literature is <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/10/19/pond-scum">not unanimous</a>.</p>

<p>From page three:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Men labor under a mistake. The better part of the man is soon ploughed into the soil for compost. By a seeming fate, commonly called necessity, they are employed, as it says in an old book, laying up treasures which moth and rust will corrupt and thieves break through and steal. It is a fool’s life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From page thirteen:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To be a philosopher is not merely to have subtle thoughts, not even to found a school, but so to love wisdom as to live according to its dictates, a life of simplicity, independence, magnanimity, and trust. It is to solve some of the problems of life, not only theoretically, but practically.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From page twentyone:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Beware of all enterprises that require new clothes.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="books" /><category term="work" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Walden by Henry David Thoreau is a book of ornate prose and provocative ideas.]]></summary></entry></feed>